Finding Aid for Atwell-Hicks Map Collection, ca. 1838-1902
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Atwell-Hicks Map Collection circa 1838-1902
Atwell-Hicks.
40 items
94160 Bb 2
Ann Arbor, Mich., civil engineering, surveying, and planning firm. Cadastral maps, showing land ownership, of Washtenaw County and Ann Arbor, Mich.; also maps of mill sites on Huron River at Broadway in Ann Arbor. Many of the maps drawn by J. B. Davis.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated in 1993 by Atwell-Hicks (donor 7559 )
The record group is open without restriction.
Atwell-Hicks, Inc. is an Ann Arbor, Mich., civil engineering, surveying, and planning firm. It was founded in 1905 by Harry H. Atwell, professor of civil engineering at the University of Michigan. The firm has been involved in one way or another in much of the twentieth-century development of Ann Arbor, especially in the post-World War II period.
The maps in this collection were not created by Atwell-Hicks, but were apparently acquired by the firm in the course of its business.
There are four groups of maps in the collection: Plat maps of Washtenaw County (20 maps), Plat maps of Ann Arbor (11 maps), Maps of mill sites along the Huron River at Broadway in Ann Arbor (7 maps), and Miscellaneous (1 map).
Plat maps of Washtenaw County include one map for each township, which show names of initial land purchasers and subsequent landowners through about the 1850s. Plat maps of Ann Arbor are cadastral maps (show property boundaries) and some show land ownership as well. Maps of mill sites along the Huron River at Broadway in Ann Arbor show in great detail the complex of mills, millraces, dams, and outbuildings in the Broadway area. Miscellaneous includes one map of a lake in Lenawee County.
Subjects:
Washtenaw County (Mich.)--Maps.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Maps.; Real property--Michigan--Washtenaw County--Maps.; Real property--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Maps.; Landowners--Michigan--Washtenaw County--Maps.; Landowners--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Maps.; Huron River (Oakland County-Monroe County, Mich.); Mills and mill work--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Maps.
Contributors:
Davis, Joseph Baker, 1845-1920.
Genre Terms:
Maps.
- Plat maps of Washtenaw County, Mich.
  - [Plat maps of Washtenaw County, Mich.] circa 1838, 20 maps: ms; Scale [ca. 1:16,000]: 61 x 61 cm. (Folder 1)
    (Cadastral maps; show land ownership, annotated to show land transfers through 1850s(?))
- Plat maps of Ann Arbor, Mich.
  - Ann Arbor City, Block 2 S. R. 5 E circa 1900, 1 map ms; Scale [1:360] col.; 49 x 41 cm. (Folder 2)
    (Cadastral map: Shows block bounded by Washington and Liberty Streets and Fourth and Fifth Avenues)
  - Ann Arbor, Michigan: lands of Anton Eisele et al. between Washington and Liberty Streets / J. B. Davis. 1887, 1 map: ms; Scale 1:480: col.; 70 x 31 cm. (Folder 2)
    (Area shown later became Murray Street and vicinity. Cadastral map; shows land ownership, shows mill race and approximate channel of old creek)
  - Ann Arbor vill, [184-?], 1 map: ms; Scale [ca. 1:5,500] 64 x 68 cm. (Folder 2)
    (Cadastral maps of Lower Town area north of Huron River, Davidson & Guiteau's Addition, and area along Miller Road on verso)
  - B. 7 S. R. 13 E. Ann Arbor Land Co. / J. B. Davis 1888, 1 map: ms; Cadastral map Scale [1: 480] col.; 41 x 34 cm. (Folder 2)
    (Shows block bounded by Monroe, Twelfth, and Hill Streets and East University Avenue)
  - Copy of plat, taken from Christian Hoffstetter's deed / J. B. Davis 1888, 1 map: ms; Cadastral map. Scale 1:480. 58 x 30 cm. (Folder 2)
    (Area shown later became Murray Street and vicinity)
  - Data in red relates to Phoenix Block Subdivision of Block 1 South Range 4 East in the city of Ann Arbor, taken from a map of said city, dated 1853... / J. B. Davis 1900, 1 map: ms; Cadastral map: scale [ca. 1:264] col.; 43 x 43 cm. (Folder 2)
    (Shows block bounded by Huron, Main, and Washington Streets and Fourth Avenue, shows land ownership.)
  - Eastern Add[it]ion to the village of Ann Arbor / surveyed in June 1839 by John Farnsworth circa 1899, 1 map: ms; Cadastral map Scale [1:2,376] col.; 40 x 26 cm. (Folder 2)
    (Shows area between Huron River, State Street, North University Avenue, and Fourteenth Street)
    (Ancillary map: Catholic Church property)
  - [Map of area between Hill, State, Dewey, and Wood Streets, Ann Arbor, Mich.] circa 1890s, 1 map: ms (Folder 2)
  - Map of J. D. Baldwin's Eastern Addition to the city of Ann Arbor / surveyed by De Volson Wood 1866, 1888, 1 map: ms; Cadastral map: Scale [1:960]. col.; 43 x 90 cm. (Folder 2)
    (Shows area south of Geddes Avenue and east of Oxford Street)
  - [Map of lands along Huron River in Ann Arbor, Mich.]. (Folder 2)
  - [untitled] circa 1840s, 1 map: ms; Cadastral map; scale [1:6,000] col.; 55 x 55 cm. (Folder 2)
    (shows land ownership)
  - Map of Ormsby and Page's Addition to the village of Ann Arbor / by John Farnsworth 1838, 1 map: ms; Cadastral map scale [ca. 1:1,200] 41 x 53 cm. (Folder 2)
    (Shows area between Huron River, Main Street, and Fuller Street)
  - Picnic Grove Addition and adjoining lands with Carpenter's Subdivision, Ann Arbor, Mich. / J. B. Davis; John Schmutz, draftsman 1902, 1 map: ms; Cadastral map: Scale [1:1,200] col.; 46 x 52 cm. (Folder 2)
    (Shows blocks between Wilmot, Forest, Hill, and Elm Streets and Washtenaw Avenue, shows some land ownership)
    (Ancillary map: Detail on Lot no. 9, Picnic Grove Addition. Shows corner of Hill and Washtenaw)
- Maps of mill sites on Huron River at Broadway, Ann Arbor, Mich.
  - Agricultural Works, Ann Arbor, Michigan / J. B. Davis 1902, 1 map: ms; Cadastral map: Scale [1:960]: 61 x 72 cm. (Folder 3)
    ("Third map." Shows land along Huron River from Broadway to foot of Maiden Lane, shows land ownership)
  - Agricultural Works, Ann Arbor, Michigan / J. B. Davis 1902, 1 map: ms; Cadastral map: Scale [1:384]: 62 x 49 cm. (Folder 3)
    ("Fourth map.")
  - Agricultural Works, Ann Arbor, Michigan, general location of Anson Brown's 1st 2nd & 3d purchases / J. B. Davis 1900, 1 map: ms; Scale [1:3,600]: 24 x 33 cm., Ink on linen (Folder 3)
    ("Second map." Shows site of former dam and mill race and submerged island)
  - Ann Arbor, Michigan, Sinclair Mill site, present buildings / J. B. Davis 1895, 1 map.: ms; Cadastral map: Scale [1:384]: 41 x 41 cm., Ink on linen (Folder 3)
  - Comparison of levels, Sinclair Mill power, Ann Arbor, Mich. / J. B. Davis 1888-1889, 1 profile: ms; Scale [1:1,200] Vertical scale [1:36]: 6 x 61 cm. (Folder 3)
  - Lands of Michigan Milling Co., Ann Arbor, Mich., Fifth Ward, upstream from Broadway / J. B. Davis 1895, 1 map: ms; Cadastral map: scale [1:384]: 46 x 36 cm., ink on linen (Folder 3)
  - [Map of Huron River in vicinity of Broadway and Argo Dam, Ann Arbor, Mich.] / John Schmutz circa 1900, 1 map: ms; Cadastral map: scale [ca. 1:3,600]: 33 x 22 cm., ink on linen (Folder 3)
    (Shows site of former dam and mill race and submerged island, shows land ownership)
- Miscellaneous map
  - Islands in Evans Lake, sections six and seven, T. 5 S. R. 3 E., Meridian of Michigan / surveyed ... by J. B. Davis 1896, 1 map: ms; Scale [1:7.920]: 15 x 29 cm. (Folder 3)
    (Area shown is in Franklin Township, Lenawee County, Mich.)